(alert electronic music)
- [Instructor] We discussed in the past
the concepts of goods, bads and neutrals.
We can now translate those concepts
into the utility language.
Utility language, or these
concepts in utility language
is very similar to what
we have done before,
but still we need to review them
to make sure we are on the same page.
A good is a commodity, so that
if its consumption increases,
the utility level will increase.
So there's more
satisfaction, more utility,
if the consumption of
that commodity increases.
If that is true, then we are
talking about a good, okay
A bad is a commodity in
which the consumption,
if the consumption increases,
the utility or satisfaction
will decrease, right?
More of it will make you
more miserable, less happy,
less satisfied, less will
decrease your utility level.
And a neutral will be
the case of a commodity
for which your utility does not change
when the consumption or intake
of that commodity changes,
you don't care if you have more,
you don't care if you have less.
Oh, sorry.
This is one of those important homeworks
that you will need to do at home.
It is not for a grade.
But it is very, very important,
and you should go do it,
go try it, and if you don't get it,
please feel free to contact
the instructor, or your TA,
and we will help you,
make sure you also check this discussion
in the textbook, or the notes.
Alright, let's learn how we
draw indifference curves, okay?
So, remember, we have a
utility function, okay?
And so the first step to
draw an indifference curve
is to identify the
utility function itself,
what exact functional shape
that utility function has.
And then set that utility function, yes,
to equal to a constant
level, K, and why is that,
it's because, in an indifference curve,
the utility level is the same,
it's equal to some number,
In this case we're saying it's gonna be K.
So K could be five, K
could be 10, whatever.
Depends on your example
or what you want to do,
but in general, you have
to set utility equals
to some constant value K.
Then, from these equations,
you need to solve for X two,
in terms of K and X one.
Once you have solved for X two,
then you can give an arbitrary value to K,
and then draw the curve.
Typically, you do not
want to draw only one,
you might want to draw more than one,
in that case, choose another value for K,
or a bunch of other values for K,
and draw all the corresponding
indifference curves.
Again, we are going to do
some of these examples,
or a couple of examples,
on the iPad, so, let's see.
Example.
Okay, so, let's start with
the simple utility function.
Okay?
It's going to be X one
square root, X two, okay?
This is the same as this,
in case you didn't notice.
Okay.
That is the first time.
That is the first step,
identifying the utility function,
so we're gonna call this step one.
Step two is setting it
equal to some level.
Okay, so, we're gonna say,
utility is going to be, sorry.
It's going to be equal to sum level K.
Third step is we solve for X two.
So that means that we need
to do the solution for X two
from the previous equation,
which simply is gonna take us to this.
Okay?
And then from this, we can draw.
Well, actually, before we draw it,
let's say K equals five,
meaning the utility level five, okay?
So in that case, X two
is going to be five,
divided by square root of X one.
Okay, so, you possibly have
learned how to draw this
in your calculus, or other math classes.
But I can do it here in
case you have forgotten
An indifference curve like this
will be something like this, okay,
we'll add an indifference
curve for this function,
will be like this.
If you don't want to have only one
you want to have more than
one, we can say, okay,
how about utility level equals 10?
Now X two, the new indifference curve.
There is one indifference curve.
The new indifference curve will be 10,
divided by square root of X one.
And if you want to draw
that new indifferent curve,
it will turn out to be
something like this.
From now on, we're going to
sometimes write like this.
Indifference curve for utility level 10,
and this previous one
was indifference curve
for utility level five,
to denote precisely the utility
level at which or for which
we're drawing that indifference curve.
One very useful tool I recommend you learn
if you have not yet used it,
but I think most of you or many of you
might have used it already
you just need to use it more
for this class, is desmos.com,
it's an open source free
online graphing calculator,
it's actually more than that,
it can help you do many
things, but, in this class,
I recommend you use it mainly,
or at least in the beginning,
mainly for drawing, for
example, indifference curves.
And getting a sense of how they work.
For example, instead of using X one X two
I've used X and Y here,
for X axis, Y axis.
And this would be the
indifference curve, for example,
we just did, for the case
of utility level five.
We could also do the
case of utility level 10,
which in the example was simply like this.
Correct that.
As you can see, the utility level 10
generates an indifference curve
that is farther away from the
origin as we would expect.
Because this preference
obviously satisfies monotonicity,
more is better.
So having more utility
level will require to have,
or will be associated to
have larger bundles, okay?
So, I recommend you learn,
Desmos is a very useful tool.
And as you can see in the online notes
you will find that many of
the figures we are using
are indeed done in Desmos
for you to go and look at
how we have generated them.
Let's do another example,
with another utility function.
For also drawing indifference curve.
So, in this example,
we will have utility equals X
one, plus X two, square root.
Okay?
So in this example,
we will also try to draw
the indifference curve.
The first step was to
identify the utility function,
which we just did.
The second step would
be to set the utility
equal to some level K,
which is what we're going to do right now.
The third step was to
give that K some value,
let's just give it five again.
What happened, okay, five again.
And then, be ready to solve for X two.
And then we just solve for X two,
so in this case, to solve for X two,
we need to subtract X one
from both sides first,
and then we can square both sides,
and then we will have
five minus X one square.
Okay, so this would be the first...
Sorry, not the first.
This would be the graph or the equation
for the indifference
curve, in this example.
So we can go to Desmos
and see how to draw that.
Let me go back and correct
something about this example, so.
We were solving for X two,
and we got to this point,
and now we are ready to square both sides.
However, we know that X two
can only be positive amount,
and therefore this whole thing
will never be a negative amount.
So it's necessary for us to denote
or make sure these values
of X one will be only such
that the parenthesis will always be zero,
or positive, as well.
So, with that, we can now
square it, square both sides.
And we will have the positive side
of the parenthesis meaning,
for X between zero and five square.
So if we do that, and we draw
this indifference curves,
the indifference curves
are gonna look like this.
(alert electronic music)
And so on.
Okay?